{"tossups": [{"question": "During this campaign, the city of Camarina declared its neutrality but secretly sent arms to Hermocrates. A war between the cities of Selinus and Segesta was used as pretext for this campaign, which ominously began with the destruction of sacred hermai statues; that crime was falsely blamed on Alcibiades, who then defected rather than face trial. For ten points, name this disastrous campaign of the Peloponnesian War in which an Athenian force was completely wiped out on a large Mediterranean island.", "answer": "<b>Sicilian</b> Expedition (accept descriptions of Athens\u2019 invasion of <b>Sicily</b>; prompt on Peloponnesian War before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Thomas Graham led diplomatic efforts in support of this goal, which was discussed at the Pugwash Conferences. A 1968 treaty with 3 \u201cpillars\u201d sought this goal, which enjoyed a significant step forward with the INF treaty signed after the Reykjavik Summit. Treaties like SALT and START sought, for ten points, what peaceful goal regarding a certain type of dangerous weapon?", "answer": "<b> nuclear disarmament</b> or nuclear<b> nonproliferation</b> (accept anything related to<b> reducing the number of nuclear weapons</b>; prompt on arms control and other descriptions that don\u2019t mention nuclear weapons)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This god burned himself to death after he slept with a celibate priestess while drunk. This god contributed his own blood to create the fifth world-cycle, and supposedly invented books and the calendar. This brother of Xolotl [sho-LOT-ull] was identified with Venus and, supposedly, also with the conquistador Hernan Cortes when he arrived in Mexico in 1519. For ten points, name this Aztec God who fought with Tezcatlipoca, a feathered serpent.", "answer": "<b> Quetzalcoatl</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "While serving on an expedition for Alonso de Ojeda, this man decided to split and sail southward, during which time he discovered the mouth of the Amazon River. In 1508, Ferdinand II of Aragon commissioned this man to be chief navigator of Spain. This man was the first to notice that the New World was separate from Asia, inspiring Martin Waldseemuller to adopt his name for certain landmasses on a map. For ten points, name this explorer who lends his name to two continents.", "answer": "Amerigo<b> Vespucci</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man rose to his highest post after Milan Gorkic was assassinated by secret police. He emerged victorious in a power struggle with Draza Mihailovic\u2019s Chetniks. This man was eventually expelled from Cominform after his style of socialism led to a break with Joseph Stalin, so he instead served as the European leader of the Non-Aligned movement. For ten points, name this marshal who led Yugoslavia following World War II.", "answer": "Josip Broz<b> Tito</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The land for a colony in this modern-day state was possibly bought after thirteen coats were given to the Quinnipiack tribe by Theophilus Eaton and John Davenport. A university in this state was previously located in the nearby town of Saybrook; that Ivy League institution formed in 1701 amidst clerical differences in the faculty at Harvard. For ten points, name this state, home to Yale University and the 1815 Hartford Convention.", "answer": "<b> Connecticut</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Scenes of this people\u2019s daily life and armed conflict are among subject matter of paintings found in the Fran\u00b8cois tomb. Cosimo de Medici bought a famous bronze statue of made by these people depicting a chimera. The prevalence of horse figurines in the Villanovan culture suggests their importance to these people, who lived in cities like Tarquinia and Veii. Present-day Umbria and Tuscany was home to, for ten points, what Italian people who fought a series of wars with ancient Rome?", "answer": "<b> Etruscan</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A precursor to this object used by FDR was called<em> Sacred Cow</em>. Mark Tillman once controlled this object, which one man was forced to use after giving a speech at an elementary school in Sarasota, Florida. Golden livery in this object was designed with the help of Jackie Kennedy, who was present when Lyndon Johnson was sworn in aboard it. John F. Kennedy\u2019s body was taken to Washington D.C. on, for ten points, what aircraft that transports the President?", "answer": "<b> Air Force One</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This empire came to power after throwing off the yoke of the Kaniaga kingdom of the Sosso peoples. This empire appointed farbins to rule over conquered lands and referred to its territories as the \u201cTwelve Doors.\u201d This empire\u2019s victory at the 13th century Battle of Kirina over Sumanguru allowed this empire to rule much of Africa. Sankore University became a madrassa under, for ten points, what west African empire that was eventually supplanted by the Songhai and once ruled by Mansa Musa?", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A popular dime novel referred to this woman as \u201cThe White Devil of the Yellowstone.\u201d A first-hand account claimed that the rescue of Captain Egan at Goose Creek inspired this woman\u2019s nickname. Jean McCormick claimed to be the daughter of this woman who allegedly chased after Jack McCall with a meat cleaver after he killed Wild Bill Hickok. For ten points, name this American frontierswoman and storyteller in Buffalo Bill\u2019s<em> Wild West Show</em>.", "answer": "<b> Calamity Jane</b> (accept Martha Jane<b> Canary</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s forces were victorious at the Battle of Shipka Pass, securing the Treaty of San Stefano and the liberation of Bulgaria from the Ottomans. The zemstvo system of local government was created during this ruler\u2019s reign, which also included the sale of Alaska to the United States. This man was assassinated in St. Petersburg when a bomb was thrown into his carriage by the People\u2019s Will. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who freed the serfs.", "answer": "<b> Alexander II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this San Francisco politician, the first openly gay elected official in California.", "answer": "Harvey Bernard<b> Milk</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man lost credibility during the Daily Telegraph affair, in which he was criticized for describing the English as \u201cmad as March hares.\u201d This man controversially ordered his troops to fight so that \u201cno Chinese will ever again dare to look cross-eyed\u201d at them during the Boxer Rebellion. During the July Crisis, this man sent a series of telegraphs to his cousin, Nicholas II, in an attempt to avoid the mobilization of their armies. For ten points, name this German Kaiser who ruled during World War I.", "answer": "<b> Wilhelm II</b> (accept<b> William II</b>, prompt on Wilhelm or William)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Under the Natives Resettlement Act of 1954, this country\u2019s government forced evictions in suburbs like Sophiatown. Many Indian laborers came on 25-year fixed contracts to this country\u2019s city of Durban. This country\u2019s province of Gauteng is home to the city of Vereeniging and a monument commemorating a group that engaged in the Great Trek. For ten points, name this country where Dutch settlers fought the British in the Boer Wars.", "answer": "<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A king with this name codified maritime law in the<em> Book of the Consulate of the Sea</em> and conquered Majorca from the Muslims. Walter Stewart conspired to kill a king of this name, and another king with this name took power after the Battle of Sauchieburn but lost the Battle of Flodden. The Glorious Revolution replaced a king of this name with William III. A king with this name faced the Gunpowder Plot and united the thrones of England and Scotland. For ten points, Queen Elizabeth I was succeeded by a king with what name?", "answer": "<b> James</b> (accept, but do<em> not</em> reveal,<b> James</b> I of Aragon; accept<b> James</b> I of Scotland after\u201cWalter\u201d; accept<b> James</b> IV of Scotland after \u201cSauchieburn\u201d; accept<b> James</b> II of England after \u201cGlorious\u201d; accept<b> James</b> I of England after \u201cGunpowder\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In John Steinbeck\u2019s<em> East of Eden</em>, Cyrus Trask makes a living telling lies about his role in this war. The historical fiction novel<em> The Last Full Measure</em> by Jeff Shaara ends a trilogy about this war that began with his father\u2019s more famous work,<em> The Killer Angels</em>. Another story about this war describes Peyton Farquhar\u2019s hanging at Owl Creek and was written by Ambrose Bierce. Stephen Crane\u2019s<em> The Red Badge</em> <em>of Courage</em> describes Henry Fleming fighting in, for ten points, what war for the Union?", "answer": "American<b> Civil</b> War", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "<b>After this battle, Moses Hazen accidentally threatened to hang Charles Asgill, causing an international ruckus. This battle\u2019s losers failed to retreat to Gloucester Point and lost</b> <b>their supply line following the destruction of Thomas (+)</b> <b>Graves\u2019 fleet. In the aftermath</b> <b>of this battle, Charles O\u2019Hara was told to give his sword to Benjamin Lincoln as the tune\u201cThe (*)</b> World Turned Upside Down\u201d played. The Comte de Rochambeau helped trap a British force in, for ten points, what decisive battle of the Revolutionary War where Cornwallis surrendered?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Yorktown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A theorem regarding this process demonstrated that it cannot satisfy all three criteria of non-dictatorship, independence of irrelevant alternatives, and Pareto efficiency; that</b> <b>theorem about this process is (+)</b> <b>Arrow\u2019s Impossibility Theorem. A method of running</b> <b>this process is named for Condorcet. As a territory, Wyoming was the first state to allow (*) </b>women to participate in this process in 1869. For ten points, name this civic process in which individual preferences are counted to determine an outcome, like choosing a Congressperson.", "answer": "<b> voting</b> systems (accept<b> elections</b> and other equivalents; accept word forms)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this state where Medgar Evers was assassinated in his home in Jackson.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In a parody of this show on</b><em><b> Cheers</b></em><b>, Cliff Clavin complains that Cary Grant really had never been in his kitchen. An</b><em><b> SNL</b></em><b> skit parodying this show featured Tom Hanks playing a</b> <b>MAGA hat-wearing character who bonds with Kenan Thompson, playing the (+)</b> <b>host. In</b> <b>another take on this show, H&R Block, not FedEx, was a correct answer that ended a (*) </b>74-game winning streak on this show in 2004. Art Fleming originally hosted this show, which removed its five-win cap in 2003 before Ken Jennings\u2019 record run. For ten points, name this syndicated game show hosted by Alex Trebek.", "answer": "<b> Jeopardy!</b> (accept<b> Black Jeopardy!</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of this country fulfilled a prophecy saying he would be king by eating the</b> <b>head of a rooster; that man, Yekuno Amlak, restored a ruling family whose last ruler</b> <b>was Dil Na\u2019od. This country was ruled from Gondar in the (+)</b> <b>Solomonic Dynasty,</b> <b>whose members included Tewodros II. At the Battle of Adwa, this country repelled</b> <b>(*)</b> Italy\u2019s invasion during Menelik II\u2019s reign. The Zagwe Dynasty replaced the Axum dynasty of this country. Haile Selassie I ruled, for ten points, what Christian kingdom in East Africa?", "answer": "<b> Ethiopia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}